so it seems like
it would be a good thing to
you know ask you to introduce the notion
of sivium
to the kind of interested party that
might not have heard you discuss it
before but it's distinctly aware that
we need to build differently things are
changing
and it's the kind of person that likes
to consider themselves well i'm ready
for change
you know and i'm willing to and actually
i have the means to participate
in some form i'm willing to
put in the time to understand i'm
interested in coming into
quality interaction interesting
please so the way i
i think i maybe will begin is something
like
at the level of design um perhaps even
just a bit of a critique
so we've we've endeavored we meaning
humanity have endeavored
uh of course many times to reinvent the
way that we congregate whether we live
together
and in the past several centuries have
done so in ways that are endeavoring to
to
to do it in a way that is i would say
conscious or intentional right
thoughtful um as opposed to merely
uh functional which is been the
was the order of the day for a long
period of time
um and
what i would say is different about the
notion of civilian is that
the the design intent came from the very
beginning
with a proposition that the problem that
we're trying to to deal with
is let me just begin by saying rather
deep
um and it's maybe the problem of
civilization itself
so we're not just trying to figure out
how to create sort of a nice place to
live
for example or even a place that is
ecologically sound
because there's a an awareness of the
implications and complications
of the total set of things that we do
under the heading of civilization
that need to be considered and that the
uh you know the the the effort or the
best intentions
um will tend to be unraveled or
uh will fail or sometimes even create
negative consequences
in a very micro case if you don't
actually think about the global case as
well
so that's maybe in the very beginning is
there a way to put your arms around it
where the the strength of your design is
adequate to something that actually
shifts the underlying basis
of the the deeper problem which i'll
just write i call the problem of
civilization
another language i will call the problem
of game a
[Music]
and therefore is at least in principle
able able to address that set of
problems
effectively and create something which
is enduring
now it's really interesting that in the
past
six months i've been exposed to the work
of one of your uh
somebody who lives near you i think
actually tyson yonkoporta
because he coming from a rather
different direction
ended up coming to some very similar
conclusions and i might be using some of
his ideas
so the first is the proposition that in
fact
in many ways the problem of civilization
is also the problem of city
that it may in fact be appropriate to
say that all civilizations
are merely the sort of actuation
adjunct of cities so whether you're
talking about roman empire
or you're talking about the british
empire or talking about the american
empire
um or i suppose you go backwards and
talk about the city states of greece
in each case the extended territory
as significant as it was may in fact be
properly seen
as being something like the circulatory
system um
of the city which was at the the essence
of it
and in the network of cities by the way
and this is based from my point of view
largely on the work of
jeffrey west and louis betancourt which
popularized in the book scale
so that's a very very interesting notion
and the next question would be okay why
and more specifically what kinds of
changes would be the adequate changes
to to shift that and here again
uh tyson i think is the nail on the head
when he makes a distinction
between what he calls growth and
increase
so here the notion is that
again western betancourt they noticed
that cities have a unique
scaling characteristic i wish to say
that as a city
grows certain metrics uh like for
example wealth per capita
grow in a very unusual way generally
speaking in nature
what we see is that when an organism and
that might include say like an ecosystem
like a forest or a part of what we might
consider an organism like a cell
as as the as the organism grows uh
most of the relevant characteristics um
grow on what's called a
sublinear scaling so what this means is
for example if i take a
mouse and i look at the rate of
metabolism
per unit mass meaning how much energy is
cycling through the organism
for the total mass in grams if i
increase the mass the actual metabolism
only increases
at about 85 percent so if i double the
mass
instead of the metabolism doubling it
only increases by 85 percent
which is to say that there's a certain
efficiency
built in and also certain limitations to
scale built in to biological organisms
and this is common across all living
organisms and in fact common across
human organisms as well like
corporations have a similar scaling
factor if i double the number of
employees in a company
i actually don't double the uh revenue
per employee i actually
tend to it tends to increase i'm sorry
decrease per employee
but cities behave differently uh
bettencourt
and uh west discovered that they
actually increased super linear which is
to say
if i double the size of the city
and by the way in some sense hold
everything else constant
i will actually get a uh 115
increase of the wealth per capita
or in income per capita if you prefer
now that's actually a super super
powerful discovery
um and one of the characteristics so now
i'm kind of going off on my own
um uh what's that called i'm walking my
own plank now
so what what i would propose is that
this
creates that makes the city a certain
kind of a growth attractor
what the city has been trying to do
throughout history since we discovered
the construct of the city
has been to grow to put as many people
as possible in the city as it can get
and sort of every problem context
of cities and therefore every problem
context of civilizations that are
attached to them
has to do with the constraints on that
ability so for example if i put
say a million people in a city i have to
feed a million people
and if the only way that i can feed
people is by hauling uh
wheat in uh on people's shoulders and
bags i can't pull that off very easily
that's hard to do
more or less impossible so i have to do
things like invent roads
or invent barges right so there's a
ratio a relationship between
on the one hand the physical constraints
that are associated with squeezing human
bodies into
physical space in terms of largely
energy coming in and waste going out
but also what they need to do other
things like meet other people and move
around in the space transportation and
whatnot
the technological capacity of the
environment that we're in
um and then the the limitations to scale
that
are possible right so effectively every
city is is trying to
to solve that problem and what again
what west tibetan court
found was that there was a a a moment
where the city would tend to
grow up to the limits of the existing
technology
but remember because as cities
grow the actual certain characteristics
increase super linearly well one of
those in
those characteristics is actually
innovation so
as the cities would grow in uh
population
the innovation of that particular city
and therefore that civilization would
actually tend to also go
super linearly so you get these
explosions of innovation
which would tend to cluster around
constraints to growth um and so you
would tend to get these step functions
where they would actually pulse and then
of course you get things that were much
much larger
than had previously existed in the world
um
around them you know like the the first
cities you know er and
and cod and places like that until
eventually they do peter out
and something happens which limits their
capacity to grow whoops i lost you
okay yeah keep going i'm here
so this this this um
this sort of mammon desire to
to grow at all costs and the
kind of the imperial organization of all
space
and to some extent all time as a
subsidiary function to feed the growth
of the city
is a really interesting way of thinking
about what's the problem of civilization
everything ultimately becomes a feed
stock
every small town exists largely
as a consequence of its context in the
relationship to the capacity of it to
serve
as a way of feeding the growth of the of
the city
all the way up the chain to the largest
cities and ultimately i guess
megalopolises and conservations that
are now dominate our landscape okay
so then and then what tyson does is he
he presents an alternative
and and he specifically presents an
alternative that was real
in the context of the uh indigenous
uh human groups which he calls
increase and i i love his metaphor
actually he says okay
if i want to uh increase or or
improve let's just go with a very simple
metric uh iq
in a human um broadly speaking there's
two things i might do
i could grow the number of neurons i
could just make it a larger brain it can
take a brain that weighs
10 kilograms and make it a brain that
weighs 15 kilograms
um or i could increase the quality
of the brain i could increase the not
just the number of
of neural connections uh the synapses
inside but also the quality which ones
specifically are networking with which
ones are the network
topology um and
what i love about that metaphor is that
it's real right human beings actually
ran into a limit
on how rapidly or how big we could get
our brains because of the
birth canal and so we ran into that
limit we were
evolution was forced to find a way to
continue to increase our
our cognitive capacities by virtue of
increase meaning
if you think about development these
processes of development the brain will
actually create a huge number of
connections
then prune the hell of them then you
know increase again all focusing on not
more neurons but on better connections
okay well that's nice that that's a move
right so the move is to say okay we need
to find a way to move away from
growth as a mandate and move towards
increases a mandate
so that's one key premise of sibium
right first creep premise is we need to
find a way to move away from the city
and all the characteristics that make
the city of the city
and the second is our one of those
characteristics is this uh notion of
growth and the
thing that is the right thing is
increase quality quality of
relationships
specifically and you can think about
that quite practically
and if i'm moving into a city from a
small town
and i'm moving into a city of say a
million people how big is melbourne
i think about three million ish give or
take a million
so i'm moving from a town of about 100 a
small city of 150 000
and i moved to melbourne part of the
point part of the attraction
is there's just a much larger potential
of relationships there's the likelihood
that i will be able to find people who
are
high quality relationships for me they
have similar tastes or
interests or whatever it's just a lot
larger
by this case two orders of magnitude
um okay that's true
but it also has real problem which is
well there's three million
people and the reality is you're
only ever going to meet a small fraction
of them and only ever
going to be in relationship with an even
smaller fraction so beyond a certain
small number which is around 150
000 people or so the bigger problem is
actually search
it's not math right you don't actually
need to think about like the internet
the internet is vast i don't need to
have a bigger internet what i need to
have is a better way of finding the one
the aspects of the internet that are
relevant to me and by the way now
so that's another piece right we start
thinking about increase or something
about quality
and we start thinking about oh okay well
the move is to say
how do i move away from just adding more
nodes to the graph
and move towards getting better and
better and better at finding
the right relationships okay when i look
at the right relationships it seems
there's three
primary characteristics uh one
is who so
that's the easiest right like right now
who should i be talking to you right now
or should i be talking to someone else
um the second is what right as we began
the conversation there's a very large
number of possible things that we could
have in our relationship and being able
to orient on that what quickly
and well is a is a thing and then in
some sense how
and and how largely has to do with the
skillfulness
on both of our parts to enter into
relationship how
deeply fully uh how intimately um
how sustainably how resiliently how
anti-fragile can we actually make the
relationship itself
um in some sense that's that
right so then let me make another move
and i think that's probably well i'll
stop for a moment
i'm gonna break that promise i've got
things are pouring in from the back of
my head right now
um so the next move is uh is an insight
that that i had recently
and i think it's right so i'll put it
out there i've already put it in a video
but
i'll put it here as well um one of the
things that has been
constraining the possibility of ciphium
up until very recently
is the the obligate
binding of the virtual with the physical
so when i look at that that super linear
scaling
and i look at it very closely this
notion of trying to squeeze as many
bodies into the same space as possible
what i notice is that the thing that's
really
looking to be connected is not bodies
it's minds the real thing that is
actually driving
growth is mines more mines metcalfe's
law specifically
uh it's communication is the governing
protocol and the reason why cities are
cities is because up until very recently
the only way we could communicate was to
be in person
and even still relatively until like i
guess we had kobit
um the bandwidth of communication right
interpersonal and body communication
still
dwarfed radically dwarfed the bandwidth
of telecommunication
but take the clock back 250 years and it
was
obvious that if you wanted to
communicate with other people you had to
be
in the same room more or less um
so if communication between minds is the
thing that wants to
increase that sorry wants to grow to all
right it wants to be
everyone at least in potential um
okay i get it and so the city has been
in kind of like dragging bodies along
trying to get minds into connection and
having to deal with the fact these minds
are connected to bodies but nowadays
this is no longer
i don't think a primary constraint as we
see in this call
you and i are not in the same room and
yet we're having a conversation we're
communicating
and it's not bad right it's not quite
the same as being in the same room but
it's not bad and i
suspect on the one hand we're getting
better at it because we've been forced
to
by curfew and whatnot and on the other
hand i think we can continue to get
better at it with things like
photorealistic immersive vr for example
creating possibilities of increasing
simulation of embodied experience
i'm going to put a flag there by the way
because that of course can be a terrible
thing
but we're now walking the razor's edge
between terrible things and awesome
things i don't think there's a way for
us to step forward without having
both sides of the razor's edge in every
step
so what we can do now is we can decouple
the virtual from the physical and we can
render into the virtual what is the
virtual
and now of course be liberated to render
into the physical what is physical
and rediscover in the physical what
tyson's been talking about
the the more natural humane human scale
ways of life that are in many ways
indigenous
having really high quality face-to-face
interactions at the dunbar level
with other human beings frankly who we
may spend large amounts of time with
a real deep woven community
and by the way with nature really
descaling the
uh these massively densified locations
that
separate us from nature and finding ways
to live lightly with nature and i'm
going to flag that as well this is
non-trivial
in fact if we want we can double click
on it because it's a it's an interesting
point of contention to be frank
but then you've got a really powerful
new combo right
a situation where there's a virtual and
the virtual civilian
is everything right so think of it as
the thing beyond facebook and hopefully
radically better
i designed from the very beginning to
actually be healthy
but where everyone all minds at least
all those who choose to be there
can be so it truly is a global community
of minds
and that's it once you've hit that there
is no more to go right all minds at
least in principle have the possibility
of being in connection with each other
in a appropriately designed virtual and
then the flip side
the flip side of the cydium is a a
global mesh work
of illonically nested so different
levels of scale
but but really focused on the lowest
level of scale on the level of
neighborhoods and villages
[Music]
of humans living in a very
humane human scale way